Okay.
Your wife will let me know. Yes. All
>> right, I think we're ready to start.
You're
all set. Are
we on line set?
All right, we're gonna begin the
07/21/2026
meeting of Andover, Connecticut planning and zoning meeting.
And
we're gonna start with our,
all
right.
Okay, well, I guess we'll,
our
guest tonight is,
>> can hear Yes, Mr.
Good evening. My name is Michael Healy. I'm with the BSC Group representing Eden Contractors on the special
permit
for
an accessories
structure
at 12 Center Street
Andover Rural Design District.
It's
assessed as Parcel
Map 33, Block 29, Parcel 3.
It contains about
0.644
acres in size. It's
found on the North Side Of Connecticut, the rail trail
south by Michael Miller and Cassandra Lee
Temple.
It's west by Yvonne
Bane and south on Center Street. So it's across the street from the old firehouse.
This is a site that
he had a contractor's purchase I think around 1922
maybe,
there was an old alkali weighted house
that was about 11 feet from a property line near right near the existing home of Design Bane
and it's about 22 feet from the side of the road so
the contractors
obtained the variance to
a rear yard and a front yard setback
so that they could build,
tear down that house and put up a new structure.
It did take quite some time to tear down the old house.
I think they took it took it down piece by piece and salvaged I think whatever they could out of that for lumber
and then they got a permit
and the permit was submitted at the time
I think he always intended to have an in law apartment
in this but at the time the
zoning regs
were a little bit unclear
as to how to move forward with that And since the zoning reg change, I think in 2023,
I think it was,
it became more clear
as to how to approach that.
It was initially submitted as a five bedroom design.
He restructured
the house plans to
a three bedroom with a one bedroom in all.
The house is
the structure
exists.
It's already there,
there's absolutely no changes to the structure being proposed,
there's no changes to the site being proposed,
other
than what's been already previously approved.
The net difference is that
you know, it
falls in that category
without one bedroom with a kitchen and a separate bathroom that falls in that category
as an accessory
ADU.
So we're therefore here for you over the special permit
with site plan review.
We've submitted the house plans
and the site plan.
As I stated, that there's literally
no changes whatsoever.
I changed the notes
on the design criteria for the septic system
>> and went to the health department for review. They've approved it.
>> I don't know if you're gonna ever have
somewhat supportive application than this.
It's pretty basic I think.
With that I'll leave it with any questions.
Thank you.
I
don't have much to say. All the
health department,
the checklists,
the
elevations.
Looking back at what was originally submitted,
it was originally submitted
with an accessory apartment that was
taken out
And turned into a sort of a four bedroom with accessory apartment. It was five bedroom. Now it's going back. It's it's the exact same
elevation,
exact same floor plan, except over the garage is now
devoted to an accessory apartment.
The
site plan is essentially
the same
as what it was
required for this.
Not much in the
technical details has changed, really, except
the the
stairs doing such a apartment.
I did do a walk through
and there's
a yeah. There's stairs on the inside from the apartment
and
what's through the what's what's proposed to the embodiment.
Inside the inside of the garage, correct?
That's correct. Yeah.
And
two car garage.
And both that exterior of the accessory apartment also opens to the front side.
You can see it on the elevations there, the people board next to the garage.
You're most likely cleaned up and graded. Looks a lot nicer now than it did a couple months ago.
So
weeds are down, chunk is gone.
So emergency egresses
of the back?
>> I honestly don't know what the building code standards are for that. I I couldn't tell you.
It is typical with a dimensional
from the door.
Like, for instance, like, I I renovated a a little colonial,
and they specifically were looking for the distance to the nearest exit as as a little bit needed a secondary thing, and it turned out they didn't need it. Okay. So
okay. So I but that's not my area of expertise. So
I
was gonna ask that too.
>> We have an emergency egress
for an
apartment like this?
What
the regs are?
You mean two exits?
Yeah, do we need two exits on this?
>> That would be a building department
requirement wouldn't
necessarily be a zoning requirement.
I can tell you I
have an accessory apartment in my house and there's only one exit.
What used to be an accessory apartment, Pallet Master Suite. It
was the accessory apartment when I bought it.
The legal one. Yeah.
Right. The unit I was talking about is much larger from a 2nd Floor perspective.
Has a matter of fact, means to be gross. Matter of fact, the the
access the accessory department that was in my place is is very similar to this. It had a people door to the outside
and a door from the
garage
into that same stairwell.
Stairs are gone.
Don't need them.
Yeah, they typically need like egress windows, I think.
That's for
basement, like
basement room. Right? Or I'm not sure, like, the size of the window. We typically need a certain size and most most windows in the house that does comply with that. Yeah. Okay.
>> When does building reg get a chance to look at it? Did they already assess the plans and
>> approve it? Oh, I've got it. The building department has only
seen,
as far as I know, Well, building department, no. They wouldn't have seen this yet.
At the accessory part, building department has seen
with a bedroom.
Yeah. Okay.
Right.
And the same set of stairwells and the same everything. Right. Yeah.
John
>> or Wayne, do do you know if
I know that that
house, the septic in the well has not been used in,
you know, twenty five years. Is
there any
reason or regulation that says that they need to get those inspected to make sure that they're
clean and
This
>> would be a they would be required to file a B100A
change of use permit through the health district. And so the health district would determine if
they needed to do any
testing or clean out of the system. Would be a public health code matter.
Forgive me. No, this
is new construction.
Oh, I'm sorry. Thought that you were
>> has a
the
the site plan has a proposed septic system and a proposed well.
We're not not reusing anything
from from the original.
Right. The health department signed off. The b 100 a has been issued. So
So
we're still not sure if there's any
>> I see. I if if there is
if if there is that problem that is brought up with the building inspector,
then I would expect
Michael here is gonna give us a new floor plan
to accommodate that. Right. So right. The builder will have to comply
if he if he wants to see out. And,
you know, if it has an effect on the site plan and then which I don't think it would, but it you know, that's something that could be modified.
>> And is the building as it exists now have the sanitary
>> and the kitchen facilities in it? No. This it's only it's only framed.
There's no plumbing in there Okay. At all. Yep. As long as it is it's just framed. No roof, plumbing, no no electric, nothing. So
>> when were you were you talking about what we were talking about another
set of another way of egress?
>> If you remember back
to Hearst
there was only one access to to that too.
And that was internal?
>> No it was external.
This is this is
is both.
>> Okay. I thought you were saying it wasn't necessarily both.
>> Yeah. It is. If you look at the
the elevations here. Yep. I just want make door this sure. Door goes directly to a stairwell that goes up the accessory apartment.
>> Okay.
I thought I thought we were saying that there wasn't necessarily one.
But there is.
Exterior.
Yeah. Yes. Yeah.
>> Okay. That's why I thought we got started talking about the building at Fresh River. Okay.
In what unit was the property owner get occupied?
The May House. What's
that answer Jed? I couldn't hear that.
He's gonna occupy the May House.
>> And if you'd like,
can you
just let the board know why
the owners not here tonight? Yeah,
the owner is
a pastor and he has
frequent
evening gatherings.
And so he's making a presentation tonight, and he told me he's gonna be tied up until 9PM
tonight. So
>> I think that we need to make it clear to all the people that are building all these
market rate apartments that they own. It's they need to be owner owner occupied.
I don't think that that's clear to everyone.
>> That could be a condition on the special permit
or reiterated.
Certainly very clear with the regulation. Right.
But that could be incorporated into Yeah.
Conditions if if the commission sees
fit.
And
I re we remind the commission that that that whole Center Street is
a lot of them are all rental units
for what that's worth.
Duplexes and
more.
Yeah.
It's not out of character for that section of town, let's put it that way.
Any other The regulation does say what it says.
Sorry.
Any other questions?
Hearing none,
>> don't know if the neighbor wants to say Oh, I'm sorry.
Mister Miller? Yes.
>> Would you like to say anything? Nope. No questions here. Just very interesting seeing this whole process.
>> Okay.
Fair enough.
And I think that's it. No other questions being heard. Our public hearing is now closed.
There was no written statements, right, Wayne? No.
Fair enough.
No, no, no,
nothing.
All right, thank you very much. Any public,
any written
>> was no comments for the record. Written comments and there's no one else online and
no one here. So I think we're good to
close the public hearing and move on to our regular agenda. So thank you very much for the presentation and
we'll be voting. You're welcome to stay.
We take, there'll be
>> possibly considering this at the regular meeting, which is coming up right now. They
can, the commission can
push it off or they can take it on
today.
Generally, that's what they do.
How about your agenda?
Great.
>> All right.
So we'll start the regular planning and zoning meeting at
07:17.
We're gonna
have a roll call,
Brendan, myself,
Patrick Dougherty,
Leanne Hutchison,
Jed Larson,
Jay Kamins
and Scott Persson,
and also presidents are Tom Planner, John Kuskowski,
and Wayne.
Do you spell
Osacek. Osacek.
Are there any
additions or changes to the agenda?
>> Under
commission discussion.
Yes. I would like to add
another item and that's feedback from the recent Alcoa meeting.
Call that item C8C,
>> Alcoa discussion.
And I would like to add item D,
which is
find another alternate.
Any other additions?
Hearing none, moving on to
public speak.
Anyone from the public? I think Mr. Miller.
Anyone have anything to talk about other than what's on the agenda?
Moving right along,
that's old business.
Oh,
>> discussion.
I'll make a motion to approve the application.
Second.
Any conditions, Jeff?
>> It might be redundant, but I guess
I would add the condition
that the owner must occupy one of the one
of the dwellings
>> first
for our regulations.
I can add that for if the slip attrition
moves.
>> You are seconded, Theo? Yes. Okay.
I'll
agree if I need to, to the
condition.
Do you wanna amend that to the condition? Okay.
Yes.
>> My
question is,
don't know,
is it of limited time on that or is it
>> just our regulation as it stands, correct? That's our regulation as it stands. We might talk about that a little bit when we get into the Alcoa discussion,
but Ah, okay.
There's a segue from that, but
Okay.
>> How about
consider this free motion that that police we
just state as a condition
that the owner must occupy
and well,
I don't know the exact number of regulation, but per
handover regulation,
blah blah blah, as amended
from time to time. That way if it goes away,
doesn't
if that regulation goes away
or gets changed
in any way,
it
would still be applicable,
I guess.
Wait, hold on.
>> I
just wanna clarify what, we may wanna take a look at the specific regulation that Wayne is referencing.
The question at issue here is whether or not there'd be a requirement for the owner to occupy either the principal or accessory unit.
Is that the question? Right.
So I don't think
you can
bind
a person against future changes to the regulation.
>> Exactly, no, you
can't, no. Right, okay, okay. I was worried that that's what you were saying, sorry. No, that's not what I was saying. I was trying to find a way of saying it that if that regulation
changed,
then
whatever changes
are made would be applicable.
>> Okay, yeah, I don't,
that's good,
I'm glad I misheard that, but I don't think that that's a condition you necessarily need to add to the motion.
Okay,
then just
making a suggestion.
Ready to vote. Naree? I have a motion.
We
have a second. Second. With
the reinforcement of
the occupation.
Okay.
Jed?
Aye.
Leanne?
>> Jay? Scott?
Your audio is not coming through, but I saw the waving And in an
I for myself, motion passes five zero zero.
>> You're welcome.
Thanks. So,
Michael,
it doesn't become effective until it's until the special permit is filed. You'll be getting some court you well, you and
not you. We'll be getting
the correspondence and and
and inviting you to come to the town clerk's office and file it. Alright?
Thank you. Take care. Take care. Thank you.
>> The business.
I have any listed.
There
is no new business.
Alrighty.
No, there's nothing on the docket as far as
special permits or anything like that that need to come up. Great.
>> All right, we'll move right along to correspondence.
Would you like to go first lane?
>> I know I often say there is no correspondence because a lot of the correspondence is junk.
Why don't bring it up? I
don't I no. I don't have any any correspondence
that I can think of.
Do we have any correspondence from John?
>> I have nothing for the commission's
review at this point.
Thank you.
All right,
>> moving on to commission discussion.
Agenda item number eight.
Okay,
let's go right into it.
John, would you like to take it from here with item A?
>> Sure.
So I'm putting up on the screen.
Hopefully you guys can see it.
Wayne was good enough to do an excerpt. I had done a markup of the full set of zoning regulations.
I previewed this a little bit at the June meeting last month.
So as you know, the state passed public act
20 five-one
in November of last year that mandated that all municipalities
make certain changes
to their zoning regulations
relative to
multifamily parking
and
what's referred to as middle housing,
which is
housing units that are between two and nine units,
specifically in
commercial or mixed use zones.
And those mandated changes took effect as of July 1,
and so all municipalities are strongly recommended to adjust their regulations to reflect these changes.
So I'm gonna go briefly through
just the portions of the regulations that I propose
Andover change as a result.
I'll be happy to answer any questions or discuss this, but
I think ultimately what we would look to at the end of this discussion
would be a decision for the commission to move forward
with
a public hearing and a formal
public hearing process to consider adopting these amendments or something like them into its zoning regulations.
So these are the proposed amendments per 25.1.
First in the
table of contents,
we'd be proposing to add one new section
called middle housing,
new section 4.23,
and we'll get to there.
So this would be section 4.23,
which would be a specific
set of standards and requirements for middle housing. And again, this would be
just those housing, multifamily
housing,
small scale,
two through nine units
that would be
allowable
via site plan
in the business district, which is portions
of Route 6 in town.
And so these would be the standards and
based on the way the town regulates other
both residential and commercial
uses,
we rely principally
on
bulk and loading standards,
which is
setbacks,
height, lot coverage.
We don't do a lot with
design standards. So this is an effort to
comply with the site plan
requirement of the state statute,
but reflect
the relatively
light touch
when it comes to the towns
concerning itself with design.
So I would propose
that there would be
minimum structural setbacks for these, again, would be middle housing developments,
which could be, again, two
through nine units,
it could be a duplex, it could be a cottage cluster, it could be townhouses,
the statute is clear that
it could be any one of those forms.
So just applying
a front yard setback of 50 foot minimum,
side yard of 25 foot minimum, rear yard of 50 foot minimum.
If there's going to be multiple structures
in the same development, say you're gonna do
six units total and over three duplexes,
there would need to be a 25 foot separation in between structures.
Similar to most
commercial
or multifamily
or residential structures,
the maximum height would be two and a half stories or 35 feet.
Impervious coverage on lots should be 50%, which is basically
echoing commercial development standards.
I did
add a minimum landscape buffer
with evergreen plantings,
a minimum of five feet tall,
and
minimum thickness of the planting of five feet in width along the side and rear property lines,
or a fence
to create a year round visual buffer between properties. So to create a little bit of separation
between commercial uses and residential uses,
and then going into maximum building size and architectural design elements, which the town already has in its regulations.
So I designed this to be a very simple,
very efficient
set of regulations that
basically reflect
the established commercial development pattern on Route 6 and make reference to
existing regulations relative to architectural design elements.
So
basically, I tried to keep it simple,
not overthink it. And we can come back to this in a bit, but I just wanna go through the rest of the regs,
the proposed regs.
Then we get into the parking table.
So this is under section
shoot, I don't remember what the section number is for parking.
But it's a parking table, the number of mandatory spaces for any given use hotel, you need 1.2 per guest room.
We have a minimum and a maximum.
So the
new state regulation, the new state statute
eliminates
the mandatory minimum
parking,
on-site parking for
residential developments under 16 units. So single family, two family, and small multifamily
cannot
require
mandatory minimum on street parking, or off street parking, I should say. So I changed the single family residence from two to zero,
two family residence from four to zero,
and accessory apartments from one to zero.
And hopefully we will not be alarmed by this, particularly in a community such as Andover,
which is
entirely dependent on single family,
driver vehicles,
we don't really have transit, we don't have a train station, we don't have a lot of bus lines,
the market is going to provide for
parking.
You know, if you're building an apartment, if you're building a house, you are going to provide a parking spot for yourself. So I don't think this is something we need to worry about, Therefore, it is also not something that we need to worry about
eliminating per the state statute.
Similarly, in multifamily
residences,
condos, apartments, townhouses, etcetera, as well as middle housing, which is the new category we're adding.
I reflected the state standard,
which is no minimum for 16 residential units or fewer.
For more than that,
there'll be a requirement of one parking space per studio or one bedroom apartment,
or two parking spaces for a two plus bedroom
unit for developments over 16,
plus commercial parking standards. So there could be obviously, if you have a mixed use, you need some parking for residential, some parking for the commercial. So this is basically,
this is what the state tells us we have to do relative to parking. So we can discuss it, but there's not a lot of leeway here.
Then when we get into the specifics of the parking,
there is also a
state provision
that if we require a certain number of parking, let's say it's a 20 unit apartment building,
two bedrooms
in each one, that's 40 bedrooms. So we would require 40
unit or 40
parking spots minimally.
The state also provided
the
ability of a developer to make an argument that they need to provide actually fewer.
And perhaps there is a bus line in the area, perhaps it is,
you know, right adjacent to some other municipal parking facility,
and so it is a waste of space to provide on-site parking for certain reasons.
This allows a developer to submit what's called a parking needs assessment,
which can basically make the case. It's a needs assessment that'll be prepared by a
qualified traffic engineer
to basically make the case why they could have their parking numbers reduced.
And then it allows for the process of the commission to reduce those parking numbers.
And that's, again, this is also basically taken from the state law.
So that's a change that we basically have to make. Next into Section 24, Definitions.
Again,
these are from the state law. There's something called a conservation and traffic mitigation district,
which is an area of town designated
where
the municipality can,
if they so designate,
can require parking spaces for under 16 unit facilities.
So this is something that the town could consider, the town of Andover could consider, but right now,
and that would be an area that's particularly
parking constrained.
And broadly speaking, if you think of an area like that, I tend to think of like Downtown Mystic, Connecticut,
where you've got buildings right on top of each other,
on street parking is taken up all the time.
This is a place where you really wouldn't be able to add new
housing
without adding new on street or off street parking.
Andover really doesn't have an area like that, that I can picture,
because
there is the only place that this middle housing would be allowed,
this multifamily housing would be allowed is in the business district
on Route 6.
So it's not particularly a parking constrained area,
but the town could, if they wished apply one of those. So I wanted to include it per the state statute.
I noted that we did not have
definitions for multifamily, single family, or two family.
So just to make things clear, I added
multifamily, single family, and two family.
Multifamily basically defined as three or more,
and the others self explanatory.
And then we added
definitions for middle housing, again, based on
the state statutory definition, two through nine dwellings, either attached or detached on a single parcel,
and then mixed use,
which is again,
self explanatory, a mix of uses
and complimentary
uses. So
residential and retail, eating and drinking establishments, manufacturing office, and that sort of thing in a compact village design.
So middle housing can be
both a standalone
residential, or it could be part of a mixed use development. You could have you know, an office building with, you know,
four or five, six units above.
So that's just definitional.
Finally,
under definitions, added a summary review,
which basically is the term of art that the state statute is using that the commission must
apply to
considering one of these middle housing developments in the commercial district,
which is again, a standalone
middle housing development or as part of a mixed use district,
it basically tracks
a site plan
process, which is to say it is a commission decision, but it is nondiscretionary,
it is not a public hearing process, it is not a special permit process,
and it
does not require a public hearing. So I basically added the definition but equated it to a site plan review process.
And I believe that is it.
So again, the changes are basically surrounding
parking numbers and requirements
and the allowance for adding
a small multifamily called middle housing
in the business district only.
And I'll shut up there and answer any questions the commission may have.
So the state
mandated
the business district?
>> They said, is there any business or mixed use
zone?
So the town the town of Andover does have a mixed use
allowance, but it's a floating zone. It doesn't actually exist anywhere, so that doesn't need to apply. So it's just in the business district, not in residential and not in industrial.
If the town wishes
to go above and beyond and you wish to allow multifamily in a residential zone or an industrial zone, that's your business.
In this case, the state is only mandating in in commercial or or mixed use districts.
That's good to know.
>> So, John, I I
think,
you know, and I didn't bring my Rick with me, but
if you look at the business district section
it has a prohibition
about putting housing in there
unless that is
deemed to be the most effective use of the
property because we want to keep business
Right. Property for business purposes.
Should we need to eliminate that?
>> Could,
although, the
fact that you essentially give yourself an out clause,
opens the possibility of that,
of the possibility of residential
use.
And then, the state requirements would just march in and
say
it's easier to do, but yeah, I mean, it would be cleaner.
So you don't have to sort of go through that process of determining whether or not it's absolutely necessary.
We could propose to eliminate that clause also.
I don't think it's critical, but I think it's cleaner.
>> Right now, section eight four, which is business district,
the only place where
residential housing is allowed is what's called
a restricted
tract,
not which is that cannot
a tract that cannot be expanded because of developed boundaries
or a small tract
reported in the land records
not
to exceed one acre may be developed for a single family residence.
Commission may have construction of single family residences
on restricted tracks.
So I guess,
>> and that would remain for single family residents,
what we're talking about here Bill Housing.
>> Right, actually that, yeah, in that case, yeah, if someone wanted to do just a single family, you would want them to have a pretty high bar to clear to allow that. Yeah.
So that could probably remain.
Also specifically
a single family residence.
>> Right.
In the
state requires that we go down to
you know a duplex
in this middle housing.
>> It's two, yeah, two through nine. So yeah, as small as two units.
>> Not a fan of that. You know, we
try to go through and figure out where we want to put the businesses
because we've got so limited space in town, then put a duplex
on that property.
Yeah.
Doesn't make any sense to me, but. No,
>> the
other thing that, yeah, I agree and it doesn't make a lot of sense to me for the state to mandate this
to happen now
before
municipalities
even get a chance to write their new housing growth plans,
which really should be more of a locally directed process for how and where we wanna place this new housing.
So I'm with you on that Jed.
You know, if the town were looking to
avoid
encouragement
of this type of housing in the business district would be to take a look at the properties that are zoned business
and maybe reconsider if we want to rezone those as more industrial or light industrial,
which would
be exempt from this middle housing.
So the Does the industrial
>> say any usage allowed in the business? Or is it the other way around? Yeah. Industrial
>> does say that. It says any any use that's allowed in the business district
>> is allowed in in the industrial. So then we would probably wanna change that
to accept
middle housing.
Okay. I gotcha.
That's just the industrial
>> Industrial is by industrial land is industrially zoned land is exempt from this middle housing requirement
per the per the statute.
Unless, I mean, unless the commission chooses to add it.
>> So Route 6 for, but it's the commission's
fault,
obviously.
>> John, is that Business District is
the entire 6 District? I mean, we No, are
>> we can
Wayne, I don't know if you happen to have a copy of the zoning map handy. I could I could find one with Prague.
Do we have the business district?
>> Yeah. I can hang on. Let me let me me see if I can pull up Crogg's.
You have control. So
>> Yeah.
It's basically, you know, all of Route 6 is split. There's some areas that are still residential,
and then the rest is fairly evenly split between commercial and industrial.
Let
me let me pull this up here. Quick maps.
Mutual zoning.
>> Yeah. There's everything along on 6. Industrial business and residential.
>> Yeah. All right, let me bring up the This is the Crog parcel viewer. There may be a couple of errors in this,
but it gives you the general idea.
Oh,
it just went away.
Okay. It's coming back.
Can you guys see it on the screen?
No. Not yet.
Right, wait, I'm gonna stop and start it again.
There we go. Okay.
>> So
I believe the yellow
is basically our residential
agricultural district.
Purple is industrial
and red is commercial. So it would really just be the area North Of 6 close to Bolton
or close to the Coventry Bolton line.
South Of Route 6,
there's a pint Christmas tree farm over there. And
over here is Lake Street near Dollar General on the opposite side of the street where the Extramart is.
That's industrial.
And then over here
near those at Lindholm Corners.
Yeah.
That's where it's not right now.
>> Right, and then and then that's really it. So those would be the areas that would that would be.
Subject to the middle housing. The purple would not.
>> Got it. And can I ask you a question on the
parking?
Yes. Page 103,
just got a little confused because at first in
the table that you have
for a middle housing, it says
no minimum and
then
semicolon and then we talk about
what sounds like a minimum to me. Is it like minimum requirement
is is old and we're getting rid of that in
favor of this kind of like
ratio,
one parking space per
>> So, yeah. No. So it's it would be no if it's under 16 units or 16 or fewer,
no minimum would be required.
If you look at the end of that next clause over 16 units,
if you're more than 16,
then the ratios of one space per studio or one bedroom or two spaces per two or more bedrooms would apply to those developments over 16 units.
>> Okay.
And your reasoning for that is that you think that's residential
for under 16 units, then they're gonna build parking in for themselves.
>> My reasoning for that is because that is what the state law dictates.
Oh,
okay.
>> And interestingly,
is a side note. The first law
that was passed, they fixed this, in this legislative session in June,
but it actually had under 16 and
over 16 were the break points. So if you built a development of exactly 16,
there was actually no regulation for that whatsoever. Created a hole in the donut,
but they fixed that.
So it's now 16 or fewer.
So technically it's possible to build a 16 unit
development with no parking.
That is correct. You'd park out on-site. Well,
>> yeah, I mean, but so the interesting thing is, I mean, the state and the town,
there is no corresponding
regulation or law about how a municipality
regulates its on street parking.
A municipality
say
no overnight parking on street, and the state could I don't think you can park on six. The
state wouldn't let you. So if someone is going to build 16 units, the town isn't going let them park on the street, the state isn't going let them park on the street.
From a market standpoint, they really have no choice but to provide their tenants on-site parking.
So it's
a pretty no brainer
market solution, so it's not something we need to worry about too much. But in
your developed areas, in your Downtown Hartford, Downtown New Haven, Norwich, something like that,
someone could put in a 16 unit apartment and and not provide any parking whatsoever. That is allowed now.
>> But the way the way we've got the chart now,
and I don't know which columns
I think the left hand is the maximum, the right hand is the minimum.
The That's
>> maximum parking spot
are none
and the minimum parking spots are none. So you can't put
our regulations
don't allow you to put any parking spots in there.
>> No, there's no maximum. So you can put as many as you want.
>> No.
We have these two columns, one's a maximum, one's a minimum.
And if it says none in both columns?
>> So there's no minimum but no minimum
maximum are opposite things so none means a different thing if you're talking about a maximum or a minimum.
If there's no maximum it means you put as many as you want
That's that's and but you're not required
to put in any, that's the no minimum.
>> But
so what are the two columns
mean?
I
see up on professional buildings, it's got five and two, I think the minimum is two, the maximum is five. So we don't want you to
>> overbuild parking in those commercial areas, the maximum will be five. So we're
not allowing you to build six because we don't want you to overbuild your parking. In
the case of residential, people can park as much as they want.
>> Then
we ought to eliminate it from that chart
or put
>> as many as you want or something. So that's what that's what no maximum means?
I don't see no maximum. See none. What
>> what's the maximum? The maximum is none. Oh, I see what you're saying. I could yeah. So we may wanna rephrase that to no maximum. Okay. I guess not applicable
and a
Yeah. That would
>> be better. Yeah. Not applicable. Actually, first column is maximum. Second column is minimum. Right. Okay. So if the maximum is none
>> So it should say it should say no maximum. It should say no maximum rather. Yeah. Yep.
Okay. Yeah. That that's that's how I was interpreting that. But you're you're correct about the phrasing, Jed.
That's for middle house.
>> That's
for any residential.
So we'll propose to change the
zeros
under maximum parking
in single family residence, two family residence, accessory apartment. Actually, accessory apartment, we can leave.
But a single family, two family,
and maybe perhaps,
yeah, a single family, two family will replace the none with the phrase no maximum.
>> Okay,
yeah.
A fan of that either because I know there's one house on Plate Grove that doesn't have any parking and they're always on the road and it's always hard to get around them.
And it's just it's
Yeah, that's
great situation. Parking ordinance.
Yeah,
>> I think that I mean, the town could certainly put in place a no on street overnight parking ordinance
to address some of those issues. But that's that's outside the realm of planning and zoning.
>> I got a question, John. The minimum lot size in the business district is 20,000 square feet. Mhmm.
So
does that mean?
>> To
anticipate your question, this does not replace any
building fire or health code.
So if you can physically not get nine units or eight apartment units on a half an acre because of the septic system, then you can't do it. But that's not a zoning thing, that's a public health thing.
>> Right. I I I understand that.
So you'd only be constrained by
what you can
get through the health department in the
>> Correct, what you can physically get on the site. You'll
be constrained by health and safety standards.
Correct,
correct.
>> And I mean, the commission could,
again, if you're concerned about
density of development,
you could also change your minimum acreage
for the business zone.
Yeah.
>> But again, I think my
sense is, and I mean, you guys know better than I do, that things don't happen too quickly in Andover.
We
haven't been bowled over by development applications
in the last, let's say, few decades.
So if you get
an application or two that adds some multifamily in the business zone and you don't like the way it's going, you don't like the way it's turned out, we can look at tweaking some of those regulations.
This is not, you know, this is we have to do some changes because of the state law,
but this is not our only shot at ever looking at these regs.
So Mr. Chair, would say if there are no
other questions, then again, I'm happy to answer further questions.
Would suggest
that you
consider
a motion to
place these regulations on a public hearing agenda for consideration at an upcoming meeting.
>> Thank you
for your recommendation. I think so too.
What does the commission think?
Public hearing sounds good? Yeah.
>> But you have to.
Yeah. It just has to go through the formal regulation making process,
which includes a public hearing. Fair enough. This is just discussion right now.
>> So it'd be it would be a formal application with a public hearing.
>> Well, if there's, any other edits or
questions about the
proposed regulation changes,
now's the time.
>> And I'll give Wayne,
because we're
making a couple of additional changes there. Obviously, we're gonna change the nones to a no maximum,
and we may, and we'll probably take out the language
in industrial zones
that allow all uses from commercial zones. We'll add it except for middle housing
into that, But otherwise it will be basically what you saw on the screen today.
>> Right,
and now become the draft for the public hearing discussion.
Thank
you.
>> You still might make a motion to do that. I don't think there was a motion.
Not yet.
>> I make a motion to
schedule a public hearing.
Second.
What date next month next month?
We don't have anything on the docket yet.
The August 10.
>> There might be a concept
coming, you know, concept discussion.
Other than that, there's
nothing on the agenda for August.
Something substantive
or people rephrase it.
>> So I'd like to schedule it for
August.
Our next meeting date in August is
'18. '18. '18.
Second.
Julia,
>> day second. Day second is very good. Thank you. Okay, it's okay. All right,
let's take a vote.
Jed, aye. Scott?
Aye.
He's got an aye. Julian?
>> Aye. Jed? Aye. And I vote aye. Motion passes five zero zero. We'll have a public hearing next meeting.
Thank you.
>> I did send you this trial. Yes.
Mhmm. But
so it's gonna be a certain point of time. Okay.
You, sir.
So
as you recall, this is
something
that came out in some back and forth they had with attorney Grant's about
the ability to
compel the NACA camp
to pay fees
or
reimburse the town for professional services
that the zoning commission may need
for complex applications.
And
Also,
the fact that the state law says that
we're supposed to have, we're supposed to adopt
fees for,
well,
application fees and whatnot. And
the only application fee that we've adopted is
$140
for a
special permit.
We don't have any
orally adopted fees for
other applications that we won't receive.
But we have been charging those fees.
So
I took what fees we're charging right now, put
it into a proposed
ordinance for the board of selected to consider
with the if the commission
would like to move ahead.
Do you have that to share, Wayne?
I sent it to you in an email.
I saw that, but
>> Wayne, if there's something if there's one of the specific things you want me to put up on the screen, I can do it. K. You you have it too, don't you?
I
got all the emails you sent. Which which one
the the zoning fee ordinance draft, is that the one?
There you I mean, you sent a, you know, like It be
dated
06/24.
>> Okay. Yeah. The the the zoning fee ordinance draft, 06/24?
Yeah.
Okay. Yeah. Give me a second.
Wayne, did you write all of this?
Yeah.
I have a question.
Go ahead.
>> I was looking at this today. On page
three, under new proposed language below,
the first this the first section in red
where it says the language of ordinance
70 dash zero one, etcetera.
Yeah.
Actually, that is my question. Includes
a very unwieldy method parenthesis,
chairman of the board of finance, the first selectman,
and the chairman of planning and zoning commission
will are hereby authorized and empowered to establish this schedule of fees.
Why would we
it goes on to say this proposal eliminates that process and vests that authority in the Board of
Why would we want to vest
all the authority in the Board of Selection?
>> Because I don't know how
we set fees using this method.
Can we just mogul them and say, yep, you're good? Yeah. Well, you you have or
some of the there are some fees in the zoning regulations.
Yeah. But the fee for
a cycling application,
the the fee for subdivision application,
the the fee for
text amendment application,
mean,
>> that's not in the zoning regulations.
It doesn't exist anywhere.
Why couldn't
we as Planning and Zoning Commission just vote on this whole list that you have here?
Would that be the end of it?
>> That is
you need enabling
you need an enabling ordinance to do it.
The way that the statute
says that the town has to have an ordinance
enabling
establishing
fees.
>> And we can't. Sorry. So the ordinance could be changed to specifically empower planning and zoning to make those changes more
easily and on the fly. But you have to you have to change the ordinance first.
>> That's a good question. I can see living out the chairman of the board of finance.
I mean, I don't know why they'd want it.
I don't know why they'd even want to to do this.
But No. They wouldn't. I
>> like the idea of what John just said about
that the ordinance
as
far as I know, we can't pass ordinance, board selector has to But do what John just said is the ordinance itself would be
>> that we do the voting. And John is correct, John.
You could just ask
the board of selectmen to consider an ordinance
empowering
the Planning and Zoning Commission
to set application
fees.
And if that's how the Commission wants to go, can
whip something up and
have that for the commission's consideration.
I would just It also depends if
this is a major or a minor ordinance.
>> Right.
I was just following the I mean, the existing ordinance seventy
zero one.
Well, there's a there's a building
department fee ordinance.
Oh, three zero three.
Be it ordained at the town of Andover
that the building department shall charge
a $140
permit fee and a $10 state tax fee for all applications
for variance appeal of decision of the zoning agent, special permit, site manager, and zone changes.
But we're not doing that. We're charging
more than that.
And I think I know how that happened,
but it didn't happen
by
anybody
changing this ordinance.
>> You think, I mean, you think you know how the fees got to be higher? Yeah.
Okay.
Is there anything you wanna share now? I think it's it's speculation.
Mean, just going with inflation, they should be higher.
There should be, yeah. I mean, and then If
>> interpreting
70 dash one correctly,
as long as the chairman of the board of finance, the first selectman
and
the chair chairman of planning zoning
get together and say, okay,
we're gonna have a new fee structure, then we have a new fee structure.
That's the way I read that. Has it ever happened? Well, it could,
but with the, I mean I didn't read that right. Yeah, the chairman
>> first second and chairman Okay. So the chairman had a piece for the finance committee had a piece structure.
>> Well They can do their thing. I did read. Oh. Chairman of Planning and Zoning could has been empowered. I would I would like that as well that I agree. I mean, the way it's written as is That
means I'd have to have a special meeting with the chairman board of finance and the first lap and then That's the way I read it. Okay. The three have
>> to
somehow come together
and come up with scheduled fees, which is certainly possible.
Yeah. That's not anything that But to my knowledge, I I don't think that's ever been done.
And then and then and then but then there's a separate ordinance
o three zero three, which is on the second page that
sets the $140
permit fee.
So I don't know that
those three
override.
It's conflicting. It conflicts the two conflict.
Yeah.
>> But I agree with Leanne. I don't see why we should have to rely on a board of select and every time we wanna
change the rates, but that's the way I'm interpreting it. This is this is for discussion. Yes. So Yeah.
Yeah.
>> So
so Wayne, is that the only language
that you have written
for a fee schedule for extra
engineering help?
>> Well, the the language for engineering
comes in
it's
next, let's see. I should have numbered these pages. One, two, page four.
Subsection B.
Additional expenses for complex applications.
And I pretty much plagiarized
that from
when I did Bolton.
And that that gives
I'm trying to give
or asking the selectman or somebody
to
have an ordinance
that the
PZNC
and
ZBA
may require payment for
services
performed by third party consultants.
If we have to have something reviewed by engineers or whatever,
lawyers
it costs the town a lot of money.
Those towns already have this.
Yes, towns have this. Yes.
Absolutely.
>> Yeah. I I wrote an ordinance similar to this with the town of Essex probably fifteen years ago. They've been have had it since then.
>> So I can come back to you guys with another draft
that
gives that
asks
for, or that empowers
Planning and Zoning Commission to set
fees for applications,
for various applications,
and
include the language
for
third party
consultants.
>> I think that would be helpful and I know you
said there's four or five other towns for comparison so
I'd kind of like to have another month to look at it anyway.
>> I don't think we're in a huge time crunch for it, but given what has transpired recently
That's what why it's needed.
Yeah.
>> And in some cases, they were very close to the other towns and there were a couple where
there was a bit of discrepancy.
>> Yeah. It's hard to it was hard for me. I I did try to put in a spreadsheet for you guys. It was hard for me to try and get apples compared to apples. Mhmm.
Yeah. Very hard.
>> I thought you put together a good list of suggested fees. I think they're
great question is how do we go back in the Right. I tried I tried to get that training
>> But not in a way that was
not
out of line with the towns that surround us. And they're not
exorbitant
and
unreasonable either compared to our neighbors, right?
>> Well, So. I'm trying to get them in line with our neighbors. Yes, gotcha.
>> And again,
point of this,
of memorializing
this is to protect
the town in case somebody says, there's no statute that says I have to pay this fee, so I'm not gonna pay it.
>> Yeah. Correct. Exactly.
Where does it say that
you can charge
that for this? Right.
Right now it says $140
and that's not what we're doing. Right. That shouldn't be public for it. Is.
>> So in the case that that happens,
hypothetically,
then
we have to we end up paying for this out of town budget?
>> Right now, lawyer's fees come out of town, comes out of town budget, yeah. Like the lawyer,
if we need an engineer, if we need the town engineer,
let's say a road is proposed
to a subdivision.
That needs to be reviewed by an
engineer.
That needs to be inspected by an engineer.
So it meets the the standards that are in our regulations. I can't.
I'm
not qualified to to pass judgment on that type of stuff.
>> Even the stuff as small as when you have Hank Gruener go down
and check
like the bridge. He's down there, you know, once a week.
I think that the applicants should be paying those fees.
>> Methods does have that power already.
I believe
I believe weapons,
but I'm not sure.
No. I I
>> know we we wrote it into the plan for the one that
you get paid. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I guess the applicant agreed with it. And we'd have to be paid by the town and then reimbursed.
Or
the town reimbursed.
>> So John, can you work with Wayne and get this done cleaner and expedite this whole thing?
>> Well, I'll it from there. Yeah, I'm
sure Wayne can get it. I'm happy to take a look. This isn't that hard. It isn't. Mean, it looks more think I made it more complicated than I needed to. I think the hardest part is deciphering who actually has the authority to
>> authorize the
fee structure, right? Mean, that's to me, my biggest question is,
am I
do I have the authority or do I need to just get into a meeting with the
>> chair of finance and the first electorate to do that? I think you just email them the thing and say, we've already been approved. I think
that's what we should do then.
>> Otherwise, you might have to go to a town meeting. Oh my goodness.
>> We already have an ordinance that allows us to do that to schedule them, set these.
>> So as long as we're changing them and updating them. I I don't know what it means adopted by the town of Vanderbilt.
That was approved in all of it.
Okay,
yeah.
>> So that means at that time, an
ordinance can only be approved by the board of selectmen, board of selectmen approve this word. Yeah, okay. That's
the only way I'm reading it would be wrong. Right. I could get corrected. The existing building department fee
>> was
a creature of the board of selectmen. It it did not
it did not go to a town meeting.
>> 30 or three was Oh, that's that's the second part. Yeah. Was Board of Selectmen is gonna be in favor of any
>> fees that we can get that the town doesn't have to pay for with taxpayers dollars.
So
Okay. Makes sense.
Alright.
Go
>> ahead. Sorry, Wayne. Nothing. So I I don't just leave seventy o one there.
I don't
think it does anything. I don't know what it does.
I'm
>> only working on the theory that if one
of our interpretations is correct and Leanne did say that well, it does say those three chairs get to set the fee from 70 dash $0.01,
and we don't really need to get approval of the full board of selection or public hearing or public meeting or
public vote or anything
the way that ordinance is written.
Sounds better to me.
>> Just so I'm clear. Would you like to leave it that way? That that's I would what?
On stage two?
>> Unless they the board of selectmen would like to amend that and let out the planning and zoning set them together. That's
>> where I thought you guys were going. That you would rather the boards that
if possible, yeah. These two
ordinances
basically go away
with
a simple
boom. The
planning and zoning commission
shall set
>> fees for
whatever.
That would be great.
Period.
But
my second best.
>> But importantly, is what we got. 70 o one since that was created at a town meeting
probably
Oh, that's voted it. Only being appealed at a town meeting.
Right? So they they might not be able to amend that either. Right. The board of selectmen might not be able to touch 7001.
The building department fee ordinance o three zero three, that is a creature of the
board of selectmen.
So they obviously can
change that, repeal it,
>> modify it. I guess someone would have to check the charter to see
at the time in 1970, they might not, they might have needed
a town meeting vote
in order to approve an ordinance at that time. That may not be the fact anymore.
>> Right, so this would happen to O'Brien anyway. Okay. Yeah, you would have to go to attorney O'Brien.
Sound good? So, okay.
I'll have it for you then see.
>> Thank you, sir.
Any other discussion questions on the fee structure,
requests ordinance?
Yeah. A
>> good idea Wayne and John to be doing that. That's
long. Yeah. We needed this a long time ago.
>> Moving on to 8C,
Alcoa discussion.
What's going on there? Well,
>> I attended the semi annual
Alcoa meeting
last month I guess and one
of the is we were you having everybody got out there saying one of the topics
came up was the
growing number of Airbnbs
on the lake
and we had kind of we'd had a little discussion about this several years ago and
chose at the time not to do anything about it because there were no problems. It wasn't a big thing back then. But the
thought
by at least some of the people there
was that
were going from a community of neighbors to a community of short term rental
people
and that that's
different
if not
universally
but so
one of the people who was there said that, know, I think other towns have some
regulations on
how to limit this or that. And
we said, well, if you can find an example for us to
use as a model we might be willing to consider that
and I haven't heard anything back on that. I don't know if John's had any experience with anything
like that
Verdi?
Yeah.
>> Broad strokes, I strongly recommend that if the town is interested in putting something like this in place, it should be an ordinance, not a zoning regulation.
If
for no other reason, I mean, has a little bit more weight and it also eliminates the issue of
preexisting grandfathered uses. So anybody that had operated an Airbnb
prior to a zoning regulation going into place would be able to continue indefinitely.
An ordinance would eliminate that. It gives a little more control.
I would be happy to forward you
a copy of the town of Essex's
Airbnb
ordinance, which passed about three years ago. They worked on it for probably two, three years
through several iterations, and
it's decent. I mean, reads largely like a zoning regulation, but it is the form of an ordinance.
>> Okay, yeah, I'd be interested at least take a look at it.
Does it require registering with the town?
>> It does indeed. Yes. And that requires,
an initial,
inspection by
the,
building official and fire marshal.
That's a good thing.
Jed, how
how prevalent is this Jed?
>> Not sure. I know there's there's a couple. You know, I'm aware of
at least three.
>> I mean, three altogether or three that are sort of becoming
unofficial short term rentals?
Well
three that are
are short term rentals.
Yeah. Now,
>> you know, know and
that house right across the street from me was bought by a realtor to rent out and I think that's going to be a long term that the goal is long term rental and other houses over there recently
changed hands no matter what the plan is there but you know the
the flavor of the community
over there might be changing a little bit, not necessarily for the better.
And I know when we were talking about the
accessory
units, when we first put that regulation in there,
we started having a conversation about maybe
so you let your mom
rent out the
accessory apartment
and then we asked the question what happens when mom dies?
Can't And use it for anybody outside your family and we decided to do that.
My concern
now goes beyond that to where
somebody says I'm going to have a accessory
apartment
and the reason we wanted the owner to live there was because
maintain some quality control supervision
over the tenants and that sort of thing.
We don't have a system in place that kind of
monitors the long term somebody can say oh yeah I'm going to live here and then next thing you know they're not living there and we've got a couple of rental things that who knows what is there. But
you know, one of the things that I thought was
made handover a very nice place to
live was the fact that we were a very high percentage of owner occupied
housing.
If we start to do things that
change that, I don't know that that's a change for the better. And so I just wanted to bring that to our attention. I don't know what we can do about that yet, but I think, you know, I I kinda like the way Andover's
been, you know,
>> brings to have that change. How does it work with, say somebody has an
Airbnb on the lake?
Does that mean that the people who rent it have lake access or they need to get a permit?
>> No, they would have lake access.
Put it this way, they do have lake access whether they should or not, but you know, that's that's a different thing. But they can bring the boat. Yeah. They bring the boats in here and all that kind of stuff,
which has you know the problem of bringing boats in there have been other places in you know
puts the liability
for the invasive plants in but
you know I have heard that on one of the new
Airbnbs,
you know, it's kind of a routing crowd that gets in there time to time and and not
you know, neighbors aren't necessarily happy with it. Yeah. So
>> Jed are these year
round homes and
where is the families or the people that
live there year round and are these how's that working?
>> Well so the newest one
you know, was
a fellow passed away. Somebody else bought it, and and they bought it with the intention of being an Airbnb
because, you know, people are paying big bucks to come
spend a week on the lake.
>> Or apparently longer in some cases.
Well The short term rentals.
>> Oh, well, you know, and I've looked at the prices. I mean, wow. I was shocked at how much we did for a week on the on the lake. It's pretty sky high, but but that's the most recent one that I know
of another case where a guy in town bought bought the house and and he's using it for an Airbnb.
And then another
person,
know, I guess they go live someplace else now and then because they can get lots of money renting the house down. So
those those are the couple that I'm aware of, but that discussion is growing that maybe this isn't good for us.
And I want to bring the attention of the commissioner.
Interesting.
It is.
>> And then why be a point of, you know, the
Center Street 1, you know,
is the applicant planning to live there? And,
know, he says he is, but nothing.
We have no way of knowing that he stays there we have no
way of following
up on that and there's a lot of regulations we don't have a way of following up on just a question that's what we want to put down or not.
What does Alcoa think?
>> They thought that that was a town issue, and I sort of agreed with them.
Well, if they're not concerned about it, then
>> they didn't say they weren't concerned about it. They said they had no
way of conviction.
>> Of regulating that.
They regulate
what's going on on the private house, it just happens. We want a lake. They control the lake. They don't control anything about the housing.
That's why when we created the
nutrient allocation,
they
asked us to we tried to get them to do it. They said, we can't do that. That's a down issue.
>> Right. So so it is something that Alcoa would
like
brought up
to be regulated.
Would support regulating it.
I
think that's the question.
>> The
discussion didn't go any further than that. Was just that's not a matter of our purview that would have to be something for the town to consider. And that was the end. Yeah, there was a question there. Yeah, that probably wouldn't have to go to the law.
Mean, I like John just
>> did that as an ordinance. Yeah. Yeah. And then and we've got that ordinance,
we get a fine thing. I guess we got planning zoning regs as well as ordinances that you
know if somebody's not in compliance with it we can find them.
We enforce the ordinance that's that's the zoning.
>> Scott, did you have a question for me? Yeah. So is there a way to make an ordinance that says that we can't
allow people to rent their homes?
>> Yeah.
Of course. I I mean,
the the
have to add some very specific definitions
that distinguishes
a single family residence
or year round dwelling purposes. But I mean, you get into all kinds of problems there. I
start by saying you
can do it, but the question is
how thin are you slicing that baloney? Like, are you allowing someone to own two houses and rent one of them on a twelve month, you know, year round lease to someone else? If the answer is yes,
then would you allow a six month lease? If the answer is yes, would you allow a three month lease? And so, you know, then you get very closely to,
you know, a day by day lease, which is an Airbnb.
You know,
the answer is yes, but you've got to be real careful about how you do your definitions,
which is, you know, and
then you run into, you know, people,
well, I mean, how the
federal government just passed the law that prohibits
corporations from owning over X number of single family residences.
So there are ways to do these sorts of laws, but you gotta proceed carefully.
>> Well, looking at it from the economic side,
if people can rent out their house for
few thousand dollars a week and they can make some money. It's been used as a it's been used as an excuse to not have allow hotels in our town because, oh, we have Airbnb's, they can go do that.
So I I'm kind of conflicted here because
somebody has enough money to buy a lake on the house and then want to rent it out. I
I think that it's nice to have people visit our town and wanna come visit our town.
>> Unless
you have specific definitions,
town doesn't usually
regulate
land ownership. The town regulates land use.
So if you have a group of people living there and treating a single family residence as a single family residence, there's only one unit of people there at a time,
who are we to say
who they are?
Correct.
>> But in the same breath, I I don't want if I had Jed's house on the lake and the next door neighbor had a Airbnb and you got to listen to a
different party once a week,
I don't think that I would
would like that at all.
Even if it was just for the summer, I mean, it would ruin your summer.
So I can see where Jed's going with that.
>> Well then couldn't the board of selecting put a noise ordinance on the lake at 10:00PM
on weeknights
and then eleven and twelve on the weekends is there.
Would that help?
>> I I don't think it should be 09:00. Your sister, doing that. Well,
09:00 especially weekend, weeknights.
I don't know. But again,
>> that's a performance standard that should apply to any property, not just a rental property. And we should have a noise ordinance.
A
property can be a problem property just as easily if it's rented or owned.
Someone be a bad neighbor regardless.
Right.
We
>> can't legislate that really. Would be clear. During the summer you would have, whatever, 12 different bad neighbors for the whole summer, right? 12 different weeks probably. The
>> prevalence is higher, but yeah, you're really talking about performance rather than you're talking about who specifically is there.
And
>> I mean, towns that do have ordinances
can restrict and do restrict the number of occupants
per bedroom capacity of a house. So if you had a four bedroom house, you can't have more than eight people, for instance, like there's rules like that.
>> I like the idea of seeing what's out there. You don't reinvent the wheel.
>> Yeah, maybe you could send us the SX model, John.
Yep, I will do that.
Thank you.
>> Any other discussion on
Alcoa?
Nope, hearing none, moving on to
item D.
I was informed by Wayne we did not get a letter of intent for an alternate
was, it was posted in the paper.
And
I checked with the town clerk
that there was also no application submitted there.
Should we put out,
we'll put it back in the paper?
>> We could.
Technically, believe that the town charter
says it now goes to the board of selectmen and they appoint somebody.
That sounds good to me. They're not gonna do that.
>> We've had so right now in the one month has three vacancies that have been there for at least five years. What?
How could that be? I think
>> we should we should try and see if we can get
up there.
I don't know where else we can I mean, putting a a thing in the River East, how
much interest
is that? We we got a better job of
broadcasting
it.
I don't know that we use social media
>> and stuff. I was hoping that we were gonna get one and only one.
I thought we were gonna get one too, but
>> we didn't. Yeah. The person that was also trying to get a position
same time mine was, they didn't they weren't interested in being an alternate. We reached out to them. Don't know. I got a verbal
>> that that person was interested, but they never put it in writing submitted it. No.
>> Well And
they know that I can assure you that person knows
that that alternate position was available.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well,
we can
Let let's let's re amortize it and Okay. See if we can get some bites.
>> There's a Mr. Miller on the Zoom that he's no longer with us. The board's definitely there and he's growing down.
All right, moving on.
Administrative reports.
Mr. Zoning, you?
>> We have a new single family residence, so that was the only permit we'll issue for 92
of them.
I'm losing my mind.
Brotherhood that bitch is on.
Shoddy Mill? Doctor. Finro. No.
Bunker Hill? Bunker Hill. 92 Bunker Hill.
But this is what I wanted the commission to see. This came in today. They're not they haven't done anything for me. There's a proposal to rebrand the extra mark as a
honey farm. Okay.
What's that one? A honey farm. So this is that's existing. That's that's that's the existing this week beside, and this is the proposed facade.
There's really nothing
no different company. Is that a brand?
>> The rebranding was the store. Oh, they're gonna paint too.
>> Have some What is it called? Architectural features, but
the main
we're passing that.
Amazing. Almost like a chain. Here. Just another. Okay.
That's always nice.
They're
not
>> gonna make any changes to the
size,
construction,
they
just wanna rebrand the store. Okay.
>> How did you
how did it come to be that the other gas station got rid of you're blocking all the windows with signs and all that stuff? You got a good zoning agent. I get well, I can't that for granted. But did you reach out to him? And Yes.
Decided to clean the windows one day. Yep.
Nice.
Good job.
>> To go back to Bummerville for a second, you said it's 92?
>> Yeah. That's that's the number it's gonna be. A single family home? Single family. Yeah.
Where is that across from what was the Zimmermans?
>> Yeah. Across from the farm. Okay. The triangular piece? The triangle piece. Yeah. Okay. Where you see there were there's been some work on it. Okay. They had to do some work to
get it
to pass
for the septic system. Okay, thanks.
>> And this,
the only thing is it's gonna be
a name change?
>> Yeah. So there's not any No. Not ownership change or anything like that. It's spruce and So
there's no
no additions?
No. No.
Expansion?
>> Right.
I don't see any
I don't see any particular issue with it. I just thought I'd bring it bring it to you guys attention so that if and when it happens, you don't say what's going on at the extra part. And and I thought it was the new owners of
>> auto parts.
No. They were gonna rebrand and
put new signage up. Was And
for the commission's information
It's kind of not to scale.
>> They over auto the junkyard
has been has changed hands. It's been sold
to a global
auto
global auto something
LLC
based in Manchester,
Connecticut.
Okay.
I have heard nothing from them. Nothing's
that doesn't look like there's
been any activity
there. But they didn't buy the gravel pit. They did not buy the gravel pit. Oh, thank you. I need some space in the back. Yeah. The Yeah. Station. In the back. I
have no idea what their intentions are.
I don't even think they
oh, yeah. They they just fly up the deep. That's how I I learned of that.
Sounds
good.
Well, that's all I have.
Thank you.
>> Anything else? Okay, going on to Inland's Wetlands. Nothing to report. Okay. The bridge was approved.
Was that the bridge, it was approved.
Go ahead, Mr. Brown Planner.
>> So just a couple of recent
meetings
and proposed meetings regarding
potential
housing development,
two separate nonprofits,
the Center for Housing Equity and Opportunity and
a nonprofit housing developer,
both reached out over the last couple of weeks,
looking to
just meet
more town officials become a little bit more active in this part of East Central Connecticut.
So I will be meeting with
folks from the
Connecticut Center for Housing Opportunity
later this week and folks from the housing
development nonprofit
next week may or may not be joined by
town administrator Streeter, depending on if he participates in the Zooms.
Also had a meeting earlier this week with the Capital Region Council of Governments,
CROG and their
housing development consultant, Gohman and York.
The town had back probably a year and a half ago, back during Eric Anderson's administration,
participated in a
basically request
for analysis
on
town properties
around the region that might be suitable for supporting additional housing.
And so at the time Eric submitted
basically the town owned property that is behind
the town campus, behind
the community center and town hall and fire station, that large piece that goes all the way up over the hill to the Hop River,
or to the Hop River Trail.
And
so met with some of these consultants
earlier this week just to talk about the types of housing
that if the town were to be a partner in housing development, what they would like to see. And we talked mostly about, especially because we're talking basically behind this building. If you, Mr. Chair, if you look to your right, that's like where we're talking about.
It would be, of
approximate
scale and density of
the Riverside apartments
on the other
side of the river by the recreation fields,
that housing authority property. And so they're gonna sort of look at the general feasibility of maybe adding a little bit of a community back there,
just on a conceptual basis. But that was sort of a legacy project that Eric had pursued.
Again, obligations, no nothing, just they're gonna kinda sketch some stuff out and see what it looks like.
And then lastly, did have some follow-up discussions with the folks that are looking to develop the Lynn Home Corner area
to just talk through some of the zoning changes that they would need to make.
They were under an odd assumption that the town would be taking the lead on making some of these zoning changes. And I said, no, absolutely not.
Know, Wayne and I would be happy to review their proposals and make sure that it fit with
the intent of the zoning regulations and also achieved the sort of development approach and density that they were looking for. We're happy to review, but we're definitely not taking the lead on proposing those zoning changes.
So just having
those conversations with them. So hopefully they're
sharpening their pencils and come up with a proposal sooner than later. What
>> was this, John, about, they're talking about the town building the roads or something?
>> Well,
there was a question of whether or not if the internal
driveways or access ways to access the various townhouse
phases or townhouse
units
would be, if it would be like a traditional residential
development,
that it would essentially be town streets
or whether they would be
essentially private drives, apartment driveways.
And I don't think that issue is resolved.
And
it depends on how you define
frontage
and whether these things need to have direct frontage on a municipal street,
if that is necessary for bus access.
There are some of those questions that I think are still need to be resolved in their design process.
Fire trucks, buses.
Yeah.
Yeah. I mean, a commercial driveway,
commercial residential driveway
should have no problem accommodating emergency vehicles as well as buses. But there's also probably a municipal
policy about buses not going up private driveways.
So if
there were kids
in the apartment complexes off of Shottie Mill,
does a bus go up that driveway? Probably not. They'd probably just pick them up
intersection with the road. Right? The end of their driveway.
That so those are those are considerations they'd have to figure out.
>> And and also after review,
the Whispering Hills is privately maintained
and
so is the
ones down by the ball fields. Those are all
Yeah. And that's well, that's maintained by a by a management company. Yeah. So I think the precedent's there that because I think it'd be unfair to the town for us to have to maintain their roads.
>> Well, I mean, if there it's, you know, it's sort of your subdivision process. If you build a new road to town road standard
Again, that's then it would have to be it'd have to be approved by either, I don't know, either the selectman or town meeting depending on how your charter goes. You but yeah. Like the main roads called Rosewood,
whatever it is,
>> Right, but the And they also had put on their
proposals,
their planning ideas
that the
town would be maintaining their fire cons and such as well, which I also think would fall on the property owner.
>> Yeah,
there's lot of details that need to be worked out there. There's
>> a lot to be resolved. But to the road issue,
there are standards for road construction in the subdivision regulations
that they would have to meet
which
is different than the ideas presented so far
>> because they Well, they they didn't resent any idea. They they just had a black line. Right. Right. But but the subdivision regulations specify
with
the fill compacted,
all that
technical stuff.
Far as how
you build a road, right.
Anyway,
that's all I have Mr. Chairman.
>> Thank you, sir.
All right.
Moving on to public speaking. Any other topics?
It's certain it's not on the agenda that we didn't get.
>> Just a quick question. Does anyone know if the White's Tavern
sold or was it taken off the market?
>> Across all
of the
the historic house. I don't know if it was taking well, the signs going. Yeah.
I don't know.
Somebody
another individual from the temple was in asking questions about
potentially using the existing house now for
housing the monks.
Which I said, yeah. You know, you could do that. You just kinda,
you know, do their renovation, and then
you could you could probably do that. That that shouldn't be a problem.
>> Do you see monks? Yeah. Monks in time? Yeah. Well,
>> not residing currently, but No. They just have a They come visit.
Yeah. They have a
they have a Buddha there and every now and then you'll see a gathering there. I
>> thought we were told a
while ago that there was gonna be one person living in the house.
That's not particularly recent. I mean
To my understanding, the house is really not livable right now. That's really a shame because I noticed when it was if anybody saw it posted online, there were no pictures of the interior. Inside of it. No?
No.
>> That's that's a shame. I've never been in it, but my great grandparents used to own it. And it's obviously a very old
Right. House. And if it's that bad inside
>> The questions that I got revolved around is that historical
that needs it, you know, does the town has the town designated that as historical and then therefore you have to comply with a whole
series of regulations regarding
historical
property. We don't have any
district or anything like that.
Even though that
was that house, Rochambeau
>> Cabinet? Historical
it's on a historical society's
site.
Yeah. It's definitely
on that. The register. The register.
Right. We don't have any regulations that specify
>> No. But they do.
They do? I would say that the the register has some kind of things about,
you know, what they wanted to tear it down or what if they can live in it. I'm sure the busks were living in it for many years.
I
>> was just curious, maybe we'll hear something between
now and next month.
>> Hey, one other thing, how about the Rosewood
the state, did they do an assessment on the aquifer level if it could take that much
water usage?
>> That's
something that,
well I don't know if I'm speaking out of turn, but, I mean, isn't that something
there again
that goes to my
third party
consult you know? We we can ask that they do that study and present it to us. That they provide us that information.
>> Well,
if I may, they
did state that they were going to be having the land tested and I did observe testing company over at the property. So
in order for them to pass health code for what they wanna do, would have to get all that stuff done ahead of time.
And if it doesn't meet the
Eastern Highlands Health District requirements,
they won't be able to go as big as they want or whatever though. They'll have to scale it accordingly.
>> Does that assessment include water usage? Because I think Yes. Yeah, the neighbors might be pretty upset if they Well,
>> to my understanding, if I'm not mistaken,
all the Vandover is on one ginormous aquifer,
but I could be wrong. That's what was explained to me a long time ago. But
>> like I said, I could be wrong. Mean, but there's something I have to do. They have a tremendous amount of engineering that they have to go through. Correct. Yes. Tremendous.
>> But to your point, that's why we would ask for
these fees to pay an outside
We're
valuing all that stuff. But it also wouldn't be in their best interest to build a whole bunch of apartments and then
six year round of run out of water,
then their investment will, you know, they won't be able to rent really.
>> Assuming that they're gonna hold on to it. Right, right, right. Well,
>> yes. So we're speculating right now. Yes, are. And we really shouldn't be doing that.
>> It's
a part of the discussion. We're not making limitations or
requirements
because we don't,
like you said, this is speculation.
I would just hate to say that
>> someone said that the commission was pre judging there. Oh yeah.
And we're not, we're just
brainstorming.
Correct.
Thank you for clarifying.
That's a good word, brainstorming.
Alrighty, let's go to the minutes.
>> Page two, we're on Parsons Miner's comment that
say that we would encourage
to
learn towards and lean towards
more studio and wood bedroom units there.
>> Yep, and I just I don't know if you knew where motion is, I just had two
small things.
One is on the first page under number
five,
it says
e h h d, and then I think it appears somewhere else. I don't if it's under the same
topic or not, but I assume that's Eastern Highlands Health District. If
we could just spell that out
just because if you're reading this I mean, I had to read it several times to figure it out, and I'm kinda used to it. So just if somebody was reading it for reference who
didn't know that,
I mean, that that comes into play. What's the proper way of doing
it is to spell it out, you know, abbreviate it later. Yeah. Just that's that's what I mean. Just it's so when somebody comes across it again, they can say, oh,
I see that that's what that means.
And then under number
six b,
the next to the last sentence, it says,
schedule public hearing for the special permit application for July 8.
Yeah. I think it's meant to say today's date. Yep.
Take a look at this photo from Granby.
Was there a motion on the minutes
yet?
>> I'll
move to approve the minutes
with the corrections that have been suggested.
Second. I'll second.
All in favor?
Aye.
Motion
passes five zero zero.
Alright.
>> Thank you very much everybody and,
the next regular scheduled meeting is August 18. And
thank you very much for all of your hard work.
And
all in favor of adjournment.
Aye.
Aye. Aye. Aye.